# Cyndia Cao

PHD CANDIDATE · MECHANICAL ENGINEERING · UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, BERKELEY

My goal is to use my research experience to deploy technology from the lab into the field in order to address technical barriers to mitigating climate change, such as long-duration storage, green hydrogen generation, and carbon capture. I am a hands-on, experimentally-driven, and theory-motivated builder who enjoys adapting to the challenge at hand.

Education\_

#### University of California, Berkeley

Berkeley, CA

2018-present

PhD - Mechanical Engineering

- NASA Space Technology Research Fellow (2019)
- Advisors: Hannah Stuart, Dennis Lieu
- Thesis: Roving around the moon and Mars: strategic wheel slip control and active weight redistribution for augmenting wheeled mobility

#### **Massachusetts Institute of Technology**

Cambridge, MA

2013 - 2017

**B.S. - MECHANICAL ENGINEERING** 

- Advisors: Alex Slocum, David Trumper
- Thesis: Exploration of configurations of wave energy converters to mechanically drive a seawater uranium harvester

Skills \_\_\_\_

**Programming** Python, MATLAB, Arduino (C/C++), Simulink

Solid Modeling NX, Fusion 360, SolidWorks, AutoCAD, ANSYS Structural

Coursework: Mechatronics Electric Motor Design, Power Electronics, MEMS, Hamiltonian & Lagrangian Dynamics

**Coursework: Controls** Model Predictive Control, State Estimation, Reinforcement Learning

Professional Experience \_

#### **Embodied Dexterity Group, UC Berkeley**

Berkeley, CA

**GRADUATE STUDENT RESEARCHER** 

Aug 2018 - Present

- Explored the impact of wheel-ground contact loads and drive controls on the mobility of rovers traversing loose, sandy terrain and climbing large obstacles via extensive test campaigns motivated by specialized terrain models
- Performed mobility validation testing with NASA's VIPER (lunar rover) team, and led testing and data analysis to evaluate the sensitivity of VIPER mobility performance with load threshold controllers
- Extended granular resistive force theory models and used the resulting insight to achieve up to 10% increase in slope-climbing efficiency for wheeled rovers and, for VIPER, a 35% increase in traversal velocity in extreme-sinkage simulant

Apple Cupertino, CA

#### WATCH PRODUCT DESIGN INTERN

Jan 2018 - Aug 2018

- Analyzed users' wrist interactions in various water sports to quantify impact loads and environmental factors, then develop validation tests including machine requirements and SOPs
- Produced GD&T drawings and tolerance stacks for small, complex assemblies

**SpaceX**Hawthorne, CA

#### MECHANISMS INTERN

Aug 2017 - Dec 2017

- Upgraded propulsion tubing, including manufacturing tooling, and verified its structural integrity via FEA in ANSYS
- · Tested electrical components under vibration, shock, and separation loads for flight qualification

#### **NASA Jet Propulsion Laboratory**

Pasadena, CA

May 2016 - Aug 2016
May 2016 - May 2016

• Fabricated high fidelity 1/20 scale configuration models of Starshade, an external occulter for finding exoplanets, as prototyping tools for science and engineering parties

## Publications \_\_\_\_\_

- T. M. Huh, **C. Cao**, J. Aderibigbe, D. Moon, H. S. Stuart, "Walk-Burrow-Tug: Legged anchoring analysis using RFT-based granular limit surfaces." (In press.)
- **C. Cao**, A. Rogg, A. Tardy, "Actuated Suspension Tuning Characterization of the VIPER Lunar Rover," in *2023 IEEE Aerospace Conference*, Mar. 2023.
- **C. Cao**, C. Creager, D. Lieu, H. S. Stuart, "Mobility experiments assessing performance of front-back differential drive velocity on sandy terrain," in 2021 International Society for Terrain-Vehicle Systems Conference (ISTVS), Sep. 2021.
- **C. Cao**, D. K. Lieu, H. S. Stuart, "Dynamic Analysis of Gyroscopic Force Redistribution for a Wheeled Rover," in *Earth and Space 2021*, Apr. 2021, pp. 318–327. doi: 10.1061/9780784483374.032.

  Awarded Best Student Paper.
- L. K. Treers, **C. Cao**, H. S. Stuart, "Granular Resistive Force Theory Implementation for Three-Dimensional Trajectories." *IEEE Robotics and Automation Letters*, Vol 6 (2), p. 1887-1894, Feb. 2021

# Teaching Experience \_\_\_\_\_

FIRST Robotics Team 5419

Berkeley, CA

LEAD TECHNICAL MENTOR

Sept 2019 - Present

- Mentored 30-60 high school students as they built a 120 pound robot in 7 weeks starting in January
- Fostered students' critical thinking upon facing structural failures, CAD & fabrication inconsistencies, and/or controls and electrical issues

## **Summer Science Program**

Boulder, CO & Socorro, NM

**TEACHING ASSISTANT** 

Summer 2017 & 2019

- Tutored high school seniors in orbital mechanics and programming to track near-Earth asteroids and calculate their orbital
- Assisted students with homework and telescope observation sessions and organized social events

#### **Additional Experiences**

Aug 2018 - May 2019	ENG25 – Visualization for Design, Graduate Student Instructor	UC Berkeley
Jan 2017	FabLab Irbid, Visiting Lecturer	Irbid, Jordan
Jan 2016	Institute of Vocational Education Tsing Yi, Robotics Mentor	Hong Kong, China
Sept 2011 - Dec 2012	FIRST LEGO League, Robotics Mentor	Bloomfield, MI